"Is Berberine “Nature’s Ozempic”?"
This review on
boosting the hormone GLP-1
by natural products
concluded there are
compelling studies
that suggest that
the berberine in barberries,
quercetin in capers,
red onions, and buckwheat,
ginseng, ginger root, gardenia,
green tea,
wheat fiber, soybeans,
curcumin in turmeric, cinnamon,
and resveratrol in grapes,
each have potent effects
on GLP-1 activity.
The hope is that
increasing the release
of our own GLP-1 hormone
by eating specific foods
could have similar benefits
to GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
without their potentially
disabling side effects.
But any time a review
makes a statement of fact,
like, "Potent effects
on GLP-1 activity,"
it’s always important
to dig up the original studies,
the so-called
"primary literature."
For example,
here’s the section on soy:
researchers demonstrated
that soybeans
can normalize blood sugars
by inducing GLP-1 secretion,
dietary consumption
of soybean protein
induces GLP-1
and, moreover,
soybean protein increases
GLP-1 expression and secretion.
"This combined evidence
strongly suggests
that soybean protein
exerts modulatory effects
on GLP-1 secretion."
Sounds great!
But if you pull
these three sources,
that was based on studies
on mice, rats,
and in Petri dishes.
Gardenia-derived products
also purportedly
potentiate GLP-1 secretion
based on cells and rodents,
but, when actually tested
in humans,
those in the gardenia group
actually showed
a decrease in GLP-1.
Evidence also suggests ginseng
improves GLP-1 secretion,
but again, that’s just evidence
from rats and test tubes.
What about that
red wine compound, resveratrol?
Works in diabetic rats,
but not in diabetic humans.
Green tea is said to increase
GLP-1 levels in actual patients,
actual human patients!
But, in fact,
the increase over placebo
did not reach
statistical significance.
Olive oil is said to induce
higher GLP-1 concentrations
than butter,
but the study that was cited,
this one,
actually showed
no significant difference.
This was
on healthy subjects, though;
a similar study
on those with diabetes
did show a larger
GLP-1 response,
though only by about 15 percent.
Avocados have lots
of monounsaturated fats, too.
And online,
you’ll find so-called experts
who claim that
eating avocados can be,
"as effective as getting
weight-loss injections,"
a food that works
"just like the miracle
weight-loss jab Ozempic,"
and that’s from a nutritionist!
"Guaca-mo-zempic"
may work if you’re a rat,
but in humans,
GLP-1 was found to be
significantly lower
in the avocado-added meal.
Speaking of online speculation,
what do we know about berberine,
the supplement dubbed
"Nature’s Ozempic,"
a component of barberries,
a dried fruit
I’ve previously profiled
as a treatment for acne?
Well, berberine
boosts GLP-1 secretion
in rats and Petri dishes,
but there haven’t been any
GLP-1 studies on humans yet.
What we care about, though,
is weight loss,
and there have been
a bunch of studies
on the effects
of berberine and barberries
on body weight.
No effect was found,
either for berberine supplements
or barberries themselves.
This is all very disappointing.
Something in the spice
"fenugreek"
seemed to boost GLP-1 signaling
in a test tube,
but there are no human studies,
and it didn’t even work in mice.
So, fenugreek flopped,
but there are some spices
that can legitimately
boost GLP-1 in humans,
which I’ll cover next.